<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-20T15:24:43-05:00</updated><id>https://mgintz.com/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Blog - Michael Gintz</title><subtitle>Michael Gintz&apos;s blog</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Headstones</title><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/2025/04/16/headstones/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Headstones" /><published>2025-04-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-04-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mgintz.com/blog/2025/04/16/headstones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mgintz.com/blog/2025/04/16/headstones/"><![CDATA[first post on this blog<br>
dont think it is my first post on wordpress<br>
it is not my first blog post<br>
many have come before<br>
whether others come after is not for me to decide<br>
a blog is not a monument<br>
it is a way for me to talk to you(, to imagine perception, to interpret imagination)<br><br>

<b>item 1: january 9 2025</b><br><br>

If it isn't written down, it doesn't matter<br><br>

It doesn't count<br><br>

You're wasting time and space and energy<br><br>

But I'm never going to read it<br><br>

You're never going to read it<br><br>

So what are we all doing?<br><br>

---<br><br>

I'm trying to write myself down, so that I can distill myself into what's interesting, what's important, what I'm proud of. I write down what I feel so that... so that I feel like my feelings are important enough for that? Because I <i>believe</i> that they are?<br><br>

My short memory means that I exist in a shorter time window than most. I may be a sum of my whole life under the hood, but to my own perception I'm only a sum of the last month, a collection of memories from the last year, and the few evergreen moments that persist from day to day, decade to decade. Who I was outside of this window is not important to <i>me</i>.<br><br>

I write so that others can read, but though I hope they benefit from it, the most honest justification for this motivation is that I hope that I can connect with people, even if that connection manifests in that moment as one-directional. If someone reads something outside of my window, they are reading the words of a dead man, and I am kept out of the equation.<br><br>

I write as a headstone for that dead man so that I can read it. But this cannot be true. In reality, I write as a headstone for myself, so that when I die, my future self can read it. Reading the headstones that lie behind me seem to me largely inscrutable and meaningless. I have long wished for a way to keep myself from erasing my past -- I do it habitually. But I do it because I wished to create a testament to myself, and now what I am left with is many small fragments of testaments to various souls who have left the earth. I do not see myself in them, nor do I see their own selves in each other.<br><br>

<b>item 2: january 9 2025 and april 13 2025</b><br><br>

I'm going to stop keeping long, pruned lists of my favorite songs. A song is a pattern that you enjoy memorizing, a twitch of the body, too short to circumnavigate the island it surveils. One can love a song through the years, but there is a difference between the feeling a song conveys and the feeling of its pattern, and after time has passed and these two decohere, you are only left with the former.<br><br>

I've come to see these lists as these headstones, and I've managed to put myself under the impression that if I just focus on things that are a bit longer, even just an hour as opposed to a few minutes, then it will be truly worth something.<br><br>

<b>item 3: april 4 2025</b><br><br>

<div style="padding: 0 .5in">The flow of the river is ceaseless and its water is never the same. The bubbles that float in the pools, now vanishing, now forming, are not of long duration: so in the world are man and his dwellings. <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/537a8950e4b0e00f9812dec6/t/5f1628748f86be74102489c1/1595287669917/Hojoki+translation.pdf">[1]</a></div><br>

If I can only build sandcastles, then I must grab toothpicks and carve beautiful designs into them. I've been guilty of overfitting to the idea that<br><br>

<div style="padding: 0 .5in">all of the thoughts and understandings that have accumulated since humans first began assembling culture, don’t require a human observer, or any observer at all for it to matter. <a href="https://wispofcloud.wordpress.com/2023/12/17/life-as-experiment-thoughts-on-reading-the-doomed-city-by-the-brothers-strugatsky-as-an-american-in-2023/">[2]</a></div><br>

Understanding is a window from the self, either into the other or back into the self, allowing joy to enter.<br><br>

<b>item 4: april 16 2025</b><br><br>

holy shit have you guys seen this mishima movie??? crazy right<br><br>

<b>item 5: media</b><br><br>

<i>Mishima: A Life in Four Chapters</i><br>Amazing movie. Lots of discussion about what it means to create art, its perceived purpose, narcissism(?)... fascism... an inability to look beyond the sphere of the platonic<br><br>

Nine Inch Nails, <i>Pretty Hate Machine</i><br>song that most caught my attention was The Only Time; this album is not claustrophobic, but its definitely a soundtrack for being in a small space, or an abandoned warehouse at night, big shiny fan slowly spinning from the wind and letting moonlight in to shine upon dirty insides, sweaty and godless places. the music itself does a great job at being ugly. it is a dryness around wet things. go listen<br><br>

Black Midi, <i>Cavalcade</i><br>Finally got around to this - long standing item in my music queue. Telling you to listen to this a few listens shy of when I should, mostly because I want this blog post to be UP! But it's got some cheeky rhythms and rhymes, smooth songs mixed in with the chaotic, if you like the musical feeling of having control and then losing it (as opposed to, say, hyperpop, where you are never given it to begin with, here we begin with a base of familiar instruments, familiar patterns, and they dive with us into madness) then give it a go!]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[first post on this blog dont think it is my first post on wordpress it is not my first blog post many have come before whether others come after is not for me to decide a blog is not a monument it is a way for me to talk to you(, to imagine perception, to interpret imagination)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hot summer night and i’m packing my neocortex</title><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/2024/04/06/hot-summer-night-and-i'm-packing-my-neocortex/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hot summer night and i’m packing my neocortex" /><published>2024-04-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mgintz.com/blog/2024/04/06/hot-summer-night-and-i&apos;m-packing-my-neocortex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mgintz.com/blog/2024/04/06/hot-summer-night-and-i&apos;m-packing-my-neocortex/"><![CDATA[written May 25, 2023; posted with clerical edits<br><br>

sleepless nights in a dorm bedroom with one of those god-awful dorm room matresses, with metal being sprung right into you and no discernible padding whatsoever. its hot. its humid. i may have had a thai tea that day. all the cold that it had when i drank it is long gone now. is that why i cant sleep? because of the caffeine? why i'm not thinking about anything very strenuously at all but my brain feels like it's running like an engine, pumping blood through itself so fast i can hear the friction between my blood cells and the walls of my veins? surely not. caffeine makes you alert; everything is swirling around me and sweeping me away; that isn't alertness.<br><br>

i'm begging whatever god is watching me and seeing me struggle and doing nothing to just relent and let me sleep. sleep is not something i'm craving, which is for the best; i'm never going to get any sleep here that could be thought of as desirable. it's just something that i have to get before morning. today was so long; maybe if things were quieter there would be less in my head to swirl around. thoughts of things which are important, but which are moving too fast to understand them enough to put them into words, rush by. a lot of things about how something went with someone else; thoughts which are in my head and in theirs and were once relevant to something big but now are left only to be flushed out by sleep.<br><br>

tomorrow, i will fill my head with different things. and tomorrow night, i will be here again, doing the same thing i am now, trying to flush those new thoughts down.<br><br>

happiness is a concept too difficult to be able to continuously understand throughout the day<br><br>

but when i do understand it, and i am not flooded with exhaustion, i can see that it fills me<br><br>

for a split second, i am happy. the next split-second, i am asleep.]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[written May 25, 2023; posted with clerical edits]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stop telling me it’s okay to be still</title><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/10/Stop-telling-me-it's-okay-to-be-still/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stop telling me it’s okay to be still" /><published>2023-06-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/10/Stop-telling-me-it&apos;s-okay-to-be-still</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/10/Stop-telling-me-it&apos;s-okay-to-be-still/"><![CDATA[One loud, resounding <i>Click!</i> of the metal edge of Mrs. Williams' ruler against her music stand after another, each more desperate than the last, the first few clicks simply calling for our attention, the next few screaming for it, the last few begging for their lives, each with face red and glistening from sweat and tears, veins visibly at their limits from the effort, while Mrs. Williams' face, though similarly apparent and for much the same reasons, is drier.<br><br>

"You're never going to be <i>anything</i>! Not one of you is going to get out of here. You'll just keep pacing in circles, all behind each other, ants in a death spiral, chasing <i>nothing</i> which you're telling <i>everyone</i> is <i>something</i>, everyone in the <i>same</i> spiral as <i>you</i>, until you've just <i>had it</i>, and that will be that."<br><br>

The class ends. Students quietly pack their things and leave the room. Behind the last one, the door slowly closes, cushioned by the air in its pneumatic mechanism, until it gently but completely shuts. The final clap of the door into place and <i>chunk</i> of the deadlatch into the doorframe is peaceful. It signals security. All of the tension from the clicks dissipates instantly. She sits down slowly, but as soon as she does the last of her energy vanishes, and she slumps down on the long table in front of her.<br><br>

At some point, the janitor passes through. "You alright?" Mrs. Williams, now just Savannah, sits up, says something polite and convincing. maybe asks him how his day's going. He maybe says something, and eventually is gone.<br><br>

The next time she sits up, the shadows are longer outside, though not as long as she had expected (feared?) they would be.<br><br>

However long ago, she had heard something similar, from a teacher of her own, one hated by most. Had she really proven him wrong? And why did she still so strongly feel the need to?]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One loud, resounding Click! of the metal edge of Mrs. Williams' ruler against her music stand after another, each more desperate than the last, the first few clicks simply calling for our attention, the next few screaming for it, the last few begging for their lives, each with face red and glistening from sweat and tears, veins visibly at their limits from the effort, while Mrs. Williams' face, though similarly apparent and for much the same reasons, is drier.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">why isn’t staying healthy getting any easier</title><link href="https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/03/why-isn't-staying-healthy-getting-any-easier/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="why isn’t staying healthy getting any easier" /><published>2023-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-06-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/03/why-isn&apos;t-staying-healthy-getting-any-easier</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mgintz.com/blog/2023/06/03/why-isn&apos;t-staying-healthy-getting-any-easier/"><![CDATA[<b>1: Work isn't proof of failure</b><br><br>

There is no naturally healthy way to live. Health, in almost all senses, is a rock you have to push up a hill. Getting enough exercise. Eating right. Keeping addictions, of all forms, at bay. Talking to people.<br><br>

The difficulty lies in <i>activation energy</i>, to get over some temporary negativity to maintain a more continuous, and usually more meaningful, reward. Sometimes, of course, you're lucky on some fronts. You love working out. Healthy food already tastes good to you. You don't have an addictive personality, or you've been lucky enough not to have a serious encounter with something which could spark addiction in you. You don't have any particular anxiety about when, how, and how much to talk with those around you.<br><br>

There is, of course, a relationship between how much activation energy you have for a certain task and how "healthy" you are, or how much of that meaningful reward you're taking advantage of. That relationship involves many factors, important among which is the person in question. Some folks are going to just going to have some things naturally come more easily, and others are going to have other things naturally be more difficult for them. But it is pretty universally agreed on that the relationship is negative. Looking at just yourself, the more insignificant your temporary negativity feels while pushing through it, the healthier you are.<br><br>

This often comes with what I think is a bit of a mistaken<br><br>

<div style="padding: 0 .5in">(!) Corollary. You are healthy (in the binary sense) when there is no activation energy to maintain the relevant meaningful reward.<br><br></div>

In some situations, people will reject this immediately. Even if you go to the gym 7 days a week, getting up and going might still suck. Even if you've decided you shouldn't eat something daily, that doesn't mean that the desire to have it every day is going to eventually completely disappear. Addictions that have gotten to you in the past could keep attempting to reintroduce themselves into your life forever.<br><br>

<i>Even if you communicate regularly and are comprehensively compatible with someone, it might still take effort to reach out.</i><br><br>

That doesn't mean you shouldn't expect things to get easier with time. The more you work at something, the more you build it into your routine, the more natural it will come to feel. Your habits begin to feel like a part of you, you don't have to think as hard to decide to get out of bed, you learn to soften the blow when you make a push.<br><br>

Sometimes that impact, though it gets weaker and weaker, never completely fades.<br><br>

But that doesn't mean you aren't healthy.<br><br>

It just means that your success continues on through the present.

<b>2: Make a list, keep a baseline</b><br><br>

The easiest way to succeed is to continue an existing success. The hardest is to create a new one. No matter how much work you may put in, and no matter how long it feels like all of your activation energies are so manageable that you'll never have to worry about getting stopped by them again, a time may still come where they flare up, where everything you have to do just feels <i>impossible</i>.<br><br>

Sometimes the answer is <i>the reward I'm getting is just that important, I've got to stick it out.</i><br><br>

Sometimes it isn't.<br><br>

Not everyone has to be a health food influencer, a bodybuilder, cold-turkey, a social butterfly.<br><br>

You can be successful without going above-and-beyond. Just because you aren't the best at something doesn't mean you aren't succeeding.<br><br>

But you should still try to figure out what succeeding is, and then accomplish it.<br><br>

Make a list of things that are absolutely necessary to maintain your health or put you on the path towards it. This is not a list of stretch goals. This is not a list of how to achieve all of your wildest dreams. This is a baseline.<br><br>

Mine is relatively short and simple. Three of the tasks are to be completed every day:

<ul>
    <li>Eat</li>
    <li>Walk outside</li>
    <li>Talk to someone</li>
</ul>

There are other tasks as well, but they're more peculiar to me. For example,

<ul>
    <li>If I feel unwell from what I suspect is lack of exercise, either run outside as fast as I can until I'm tired or run at least 6 miles an hour on a treadmill either for 15 minutes or until I'm tired, whichever comes first.</li>
</ul>

These are often a bit trickier to add to the list, but are important if they really are necessary to maintain a baseline.<br><br>

For some, this list might consist of things that are more difficult. If you have determined that cold-turkey is the best way to go about curbing an addiction, then avoiding it belongs on your list. If you have a health problem which you absolutely must keep at bay, and there's some action you must perform regularly to do so, then that belongs on your list as well.<br><br>

It's alright if the list changes over time. If you find something making your life worse, and you need something new to keep it at bay to maintain your baseline, add it to the list. When some problem is resolved, all of the tasks generated by it can be crossed off.<br><br>

These aren't goals. In better periods, I have a pretty passable diet, I get a decent amount of exercise and time outdoors, and I talk quite a lot.<br><br>

This list is for when everything just becomes blindingly difficult.<br><br>

On the roughest of days, sometimes just checking these simple boxes is tough.<br><br>

But at the end of those days, I get through these, and I call my day a success.]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1: Work isn't proof of failure]]></summary></entry></feed>